Guide to the Montana Legislative Assembly (27th: 1941) records 1940-1941
Montana Historical Society
Montana Legislative Assembly (27th: 1941) records
1940-1941
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 27
Montana. Legislative Assembly.
.8 linear feet of shelf space
Collection contains records (1940-1941) of the Montana 27th Legislative Assembly including the report of the House Special Committee to Investigate the Conditions Existing at the Montana State Hospital for the Insane at Warm Springs; reports of Joint Committees on Educational Institutions and Affairs and on State Governmental Organization; minutes of House Committee on Mines and Mining; minutes of the Senate Judiciary Committee; House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials, joint resolutions and memorials, and status sheets; and miscellany.
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 27th Montana Legislature met from January 6th to March 6th, 1941. The leaders of the Senate were Ernest Eaton (R-President), and W.E. Keeley (R-President Pro Tempore). The leaders of the House were E.J. Stromnes (D-Speaker), Paul Cannon (D-Speaker Pro Tempore), E.J. Byrne (D-Majority Leader), and E.G. Toomey (R-Minority Leader).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
The collection includes the minutes of House Committee on Mines and Mining; minutes of the Senate Judiciary Committee; House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials, joint resolutions and memorials, and status sheets; report of the House Special Committee to Investigate the Conditions Existing at the Montana State Hospital for the Insane at Warm Springs; reports of Joint Committees on Educational Institutions and Affairs and on State Governmental Organization. The collection also contains miscellany material including the report of legislative intent of H.B. 344 (re referendum on legalizing gambling), S.B. 75 (re appointment of water commissioner), S.B. 158 (re state police), S.B. 180 (re depositions and physical examinations), proposed judicial election bill, and S.B. 92 (re rates of state assistance to counties); report on salaries of state officers and employees; and the of State Water Conservation Board.
The collection is organized into four series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany (arranged alphabetically).
The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into one subseries, Joint Committee Reports (arranged alphabetically).
The series House of Representatives is organized into six subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), House Bills (arranged numerically), House Special Committee Reports (arranged alphabetically), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically), Status of House Bills (arranged chronologically), and House Joint Memorials (arranged numerically).
The series Senate is organized into eight subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically), Senate Resolutions (arranged alphabetically), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically), Status Sheets of Senate Bills (arranged chronologically), Senate Calendar (arranged chronologically), Senate Memorials (arranged numerically), and Senate Joint Memorials (arranged numerically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Warm Springs State Hospital.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Committees--Montana.
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- House and Senate Joint Committees
  - Joint Committee Reports
    - Report of the Senate Committee of the Joint House and Senate Committee on Educational Institutions and Affairs, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Report of Joint Committee on State Governmental Organization, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- House of Representatives
  - House Standing Committee Minutes
    - Mines and Mining, 1941 February 5-28 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - House Bills
    - Bill nos. 1-2, 5-14, 16, 19-20, 22, 28-33, 35-50, 53-55, 58-64, 68-69, 76, 78, 80-81, 84, 86-93, 95, 98-99 (also Substitute House Bill nos. 1, 46; Substitute Bill no. 78), 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Bill nos. 100-104, 106-108, 110-117, 119-124, 126-133, 135-137, 142-144, 146, 148, 150-153, 155-161, 164, 166-172, 179-181, 185, 187-189, 191, 194-196, 198-199, 201-204, 206-207, 210-212, 216-217 (also Substitute House Bill nos. 139, 142, 183) (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Bill nos. 219-222, 224-226, 228-230, 232, 234-235, 237-239, 243, 247-250, 252-253, 256-258, 260-263, 267-268, 272, 278-280, 283, 287-291, 295, 298, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Bill nos. 300-301, 303, 305-309, 311, 314-316, 319, 323-325, 327, 330, 333-334, 336-338, 340, 344-346, 349-351, 353-354, 356-357, 362-394 (also Substitute House Bill nos. 350-351, 353, 363-364), 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - House Special Committee Reports
    - Report of Special Committee to Investigate the Conditions Existing at the Montana State Hospital for the Insane at Warm Springs, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - House Joint Resolutions
    - Bill nos. 1-3 (also Resolution on possible American involvement in World War II), 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Status of House Bills
    - 12th, 15th, 16th, 18th-20th, 22nd, 34th, 38th-39th, 42nd-43rd, 45th, 51st-53rd, 57th, and 58th-59th Legislative Days, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - House Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-12, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
- Senate
  - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
    - Senate Judiciary Committee, 1941 January 20-February 17 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Senate Bills
    - Bill nos. 1-7, 11-12, 14-23, 25-27, 29-33, 35-36, 38-40, 42-44, 55, 57-65, 67-68, 70, 72-73, 75-80, 82, 84-92, 97-99 (also Substitute Senate Bill nos. 1, 11, 18, 67, 78), 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
    - Bill nos. 100-101, 104-116, 119, 121, 123-132, 135-137, 142, 145-148, 150, 153-155, 158-162, 164, 167, 169-170, 173, 175-186, 189, 191-192, 194-195 (also Substitute Senate Bill nos. 116, 128, 189) (Box-folder 1 / 13-14)
  - Senate Resolutions
    - re Governor's recess nominations, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Senate Joint Resolutions
    - Bill nos. 1-2, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Status Sheets of Senate Bills
    - 35th, 37th, 39th-40th, 44th-45th, 48th, 51st-53rd, 58th-60th Legislative Days; final status, 1941 February 8-March 6 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Senate Calendar
    - 27th Legislative Day, 1941 February 1 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Senate Memorials
    - Bill no. 4 (also re deaths of John H. Leuthold, J.C.F. Siegfreidt, and Thomas Kane), 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Senate Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-7, 9-16, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
- Miscellany
  - The Capital Building Its History Its Appointments Its Art, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - Governor's report of pardons, communications of sentences and remission of fines (January 1939-January 1941), 1941 January 14 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
  - List of Montana Legislative Assembly members, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
  - List of Senate and House Standing Committees, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - "Out of State Travel Authorized for State Officers and Employees January 1, 1939 to December 1940...", 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
  - Report on legislative intent of H.B. 344 (re referendum on legalizing gambling); S.B. 75 (re appointment of water commissioner); S.B. 158 (re state police); S.B. 180 (re depositions and physical examinations); proposed judicial election bill; and S.B. 92 (re rates of state assistance to counties), 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
  - Report on salaries of state officers and employees (arranged by department and board), 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
  - Report on State Water Conservation Board, Dec. 31, 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
  - Reports of Montana Education Association on H.B. nos. 88-89, 104, 144, 210, 238-239, 345; transportation bill; and Eastern Montana State Normal School students, 1941 (Box-folder 1 / 29)